Commemorating the day the Buddha was born, we ask you to follow in his
Kỷ niệm ngày Đức Phật đang xin chúng con
footsteps, a joyful procession celebrating the
theo bước chân tâm đoàn nhệu mừng Đức
Buddha's birth, the Bodhisattva's birth, the Bodhisattva's birth, the
Phật đàn sinh Bồ Tát tất đạt
Bodhisattva's birth, the countless eons of merit, the flying sword of enlightenment, the
đà a tăng kỳ kiếp tạo lòng công đức bay
night of the eon, when he was born, the
đao bồ đề đêm kiếp qu khi vừa đàn sinh
pure heart, the flower-headed man, the farmer
lòng trắng chế đầu hoa xên nông
[music]
[âm nhạc]
Waiting to follow in his footsteps, we
Chờ theo bước trên đoàn chúng con nhiều
stop, the Buddha's
ngừng đức Phật tà
birth, the
xy ta thân đàn đá khi vừa đàn sinh Đi
miraculous procession, seven steps,
diễu nhiệm màu chân đi bảy bước hướng về
where to go, the hearts of the people, the path for all
đâu dạ người dân đường cho các chung
beings, compassion, to distribute
sinh thương về phân
blessings, the human boat, the incense,
đ phước lành bắp chốn nhân thuyền hương
to the west, the final eon, the Bodhisattva's path, the
về phương tây là kếp cuối cùng hành bồ
incense, to the direction of the deceased, right in
tát đạo hương về phương vong ngay trong
this lifetime, witnessing the bitterness of the cloud-like light. More than
kiếp này chứng đắng vân quang
2600 years ago, the Buddha was
Hơn 2600 năm về trước, Đức Phật đã đản
born in Lumbini Garden.  His birth
sinh tại vườn Lâm Tỳ Ni. Sự đản sinh của
brought light to this world,
ngài mang ánh sáng đến thế gian này, phá
dispelling the dark night of ignorance and false
tan đi màn đêm u tối của vô minh và tà
views.
kiến.
Although we were born in this degenerate age,
Chúng con tuy sinh trong thời mạt
we still have the opportunity to practice
pháp nhưng chúng con vẫn được thực hành
his teachings
giáo pháp của
.  Through his teachings, we
ngài. Từ giáo pháp của ngài mà chúng con
have attained
được giác
enlightenment and been freed to some extent from the
ngộ, chúng con được giải thoát một phần
defilements of our minds.  And that
nào những tâm cấu uế. Và điều đó đã mang
brought us happiness; we
lại cho chúng con hạnh phúc, chúng con
learned to live with a liberated mind.
biết sống với tâm giải thoát.
No longer consumed by greed, anger, and hatred
không bị những tâm tham lam sân giận
.  With
thiêu đốt nhiều nữa. Chúng con với sự
liberation and happiness in mind, we
thoát, với sự hạnh phúc, chúng con xin
humbly offer our respects to Your birth, Your
đành lễ sự đàn sinh của Ngài, sự đản
noble birth, Your wondrous birth that
sinh cao quý, sự đản sinh vi diệu mang
brings happiness to all beings, and brings
đến hạnh phúc cho chúng sinh, mang đến
happiness to us.   How joyful it is to be
hạnh phúc cho chúng con.
separated by life's hardships.  How
Vui thay phân xa đời. Vui thay pha được
joyful it is to be able to grow old, how joyful it is to increase harmony, how joyful it is to cultivate harmony
già vui thay tăng hòa hợp hòa hợp tu vui
.  How joyful it is that the Buddha was born.  How joyful it is to teach the Dharma, how
thay. Vui thay Phật ra đời. Vui thay pha
joyful it is to cultivate harmony among the monks, how joyful it is to practice the Dharma in harmony
đường giảng vui thay tăng hòa hợp hòa
!  Can one change being human, can one change
thay. Có thay được làm người có thay
living, can one change hearing about the destruction of the empire, can one change having the
được sống còn có thay nghe diệt bá có
power to be born into this world, can one change being human?  I
tay vận ra đời có thay đù làm người. Con
see the scent of life, I hear the machine, still far from worldly
thấy hương sống con nghe máy vẫn xa đời
joy, still far from worldly joy, the Dharma path is
vui thay vẫn xa đời vui thay pháp đường
joyful, harmony is joyful, the practice is joyful, separation from worldly joy, the
giàng vui thay tức hòa hồm hòa hồm tu
path is joyful, the Sangha is harmonious, the
pha đường giàng vui thay tăng hòa hợp
harmony is joyful, the Sangha is harmonious, the
hòa hợp vui thay vui thay tăng hòa hợp
rose sits, poetry, the flower
hồng bố ngồi thơ
is joyful
Hoa hơ có vui
[music],
[âm nhạc]
poetry, flower
thơ hoa
harmony, joyful poetry
hợp vui thơ